Guide to the Elizabeth Greene Gardiner papers, 1847-1968.
Gardiner, Elizabeth Greene papers, 1847-1968.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Elizabeth Greene Gardiner papers, 1847-1968, 1910-1968 (bulk)
2996
Elizabeth Greene Gardiner, 1890-
4 cubic ft.
Correspondence, photographs, identification papers, essays, pamphlets, poems, prayers, and memorabilia.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Primarily letters written by Elizabeth Gardiner to members of her family and friends concerning her personal life and her professional career as a social worker and professor. Also, photographs, official identification papers, her student essays, pamphlets, poems, prayers and memorabilia; and correspondence of other family members and friends.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Elizabeth Greene Gardiner was a social worker and professor. She served as a nurse's aide with the Italian Red Cross in Imola, Italy (1915-1916) and with the British Expeditionary Force in France (1917-1919). She was involved in medical social work on Ellis Island (1919-1922) and at the University of Pennsylvania Hospital (1926-1928). From 1928 to 1938 she was assistant professor at the University of Minnesota; during 1931 she served as exchange lecturer at the University of Liverpool, England. She also served as a consultant for the National Society for the Prevention of Blindness (1939-1942), an analyst of convalescent homes for the Committee on Convalescent Care Practice, New York City (1942-1943), and as a Welfare Officer for the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration in Egypt, Italy and Germany (1944-1946); also intermittently for the Citizen's Committee on Displaced Persons, New York City, the American Committee for Emigre Scholars, Writers and Artists, New York City, and the Travelers Aid Society, Nashville, Tennessee. Gardiner received her academic training at Simmons College School of Social Work, Columbia University, and the University of Chicago. She was involved in numerous professional organizations, and visited many social, health, and educational agencies in Europe and Asia.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Primarily letters written by Elizabeth Gardiner to members of her family and friends concerning her personal life and her professional career as a social worker and professor. Also, photographs, official identification papers, her student essays, pamphlets, poems, prayers and memorabilia; and correspondence of other family members and friends, including letters written by Elizabeth Gardiner's mother, Eliza Doane Gardiner, to Ellen Parkman Vaughan.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Gardiner, Elizabeth Greene, 1890-; Gardiner, Eliza Doane.; Vaughan, Ellen Parkman, 1873-1912.; American Committee for Emigre Scholars, Writers and Artists (New York, N.Y.); Citizen's Committee on Displaced Persons (New York, N.Y.); Committee on Convalescent Care Practice (New York, N.Y.); Great Britain--Armed Forces--British Expeditionary Force.; National Society for the Prevention of Blindness.; Red Cross. Italy. Italian National Red Cross.; Travelers Aid Society (Nashville, Tenn.); United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration.; University of Liverpool.; University of Pennsylvania.
Subjects:
Public health.; Social service.; Women--Diaries.; Women college teachers.; Social workers.
Places:
Ellis Island (N.J. and N.Y.)
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographic prints.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Personal papers and correspondence of Elizabeth G. Gardiner; mostly letters from Eliza Greene Doane Gardiner to Ellen T. Parkman; also early family letters. Beginning 1910, letters from Elizabeth to sisters.
Boxes 1-8
Series II. Subject files dealing with Elizabeth Gardiner's career as social worker in areas such as UNRRA, American Association of Social Workers and Citizens Committee for Displaced Persons. Includes correspondence, reports, news clippings, photographs, pamphlets.
Boxes 9-12
Series III. Photographs and memorabilia, and postal cards mainly from travel.
Boxes 13-14 and Mapcase
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Personal papers and correspondence
  - Biographical materials, 1952, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1847, 1862, 1871- (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1875-1877 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1878-1879 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1880-1885 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1890, 1893, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1900, 1904-1908 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1910-1911 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Elizabeth Gardiner scrapbook, June-July 1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Elizabeth Gardiner scrapbook, Aug.-Sept. 1915 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Elizabeth Gardiner scrapbook, Oct.-Dec. 1915 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Elizabeth Gardiner scrapbook, Jan.-Mar. 1916 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Elizabeth Gardiner scrapbook, Apr.-July 1916 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Elizabeth Gardiner scrapbook, Aug.-Oct. 1916 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-Mar. 1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Apr.-May 1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, June-Aug. 1917 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Sept.-Nov. 1917 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Dec. 1917, ca. 1917 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-Apr. 1918 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May-Oct. 1918 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Nov.-Dec. 1918 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1922 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1923-1924 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1926-1927 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1934-1935 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1941 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-June 1944 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, July-Dec. 1944 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-May 1945 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, June-Aug. 1945 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Sept.-Dec. 1945 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-Mar. 1946 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Apr.-June 1946 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, July-Dec. 1946 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-Mar. 1947 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Apr.-Dec. 1947 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-June 1948 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, July-Dec. 1948 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-Sept. 1949 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Oct.-Dec. 1949 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-Apr. 1950 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May-Dec. 1950 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1968 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (pre-1910?) (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (post-1910?) (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Doane-Gardiner Furniture Inventory (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Gardiner Estate, Northeast Harbor, Maine (blueprint), 1920 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Doane-Gardiner Family Newsclippings, 1879, 1912-1958 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Elizabeth Gardiner Identification Papers, 1917, 1925, 1945, 1952, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Papers and Memorabilia, 1878, 1913-1969 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Poems and Prayers, 1944-1945, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Early family photographs (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Elizabeth Gardiner Diaries (some travel accounts, engagements, addresses) 1916, 1919, 1921-1922, 1939-1944, 1946-1968 (Box 8)
  - Elizabeth Gardiner Passports and Visas 1916, 1922, 1925, 1931, 1938, 1944-1945, 1951, 1961 (Box 8)
- Series II. Subject files
  - "AASW - 1949-1950", 1948-1953 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - American Association of Social Workers, 1953-1954 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "AASW - International Social Work Committee - Middle Tennessee Chapter up to Jan. 1955", 1949-1955 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - AASW Stamp Project, 1949-1954 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - American Indian Missions, 1902, 1914, 1926 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - "Demonstrations of Medical Social Work in Eye Clinics", 1942 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Displaced Persons, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Ellis Island, 1921-1923 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - "Fight for Freedom, Inc.", 1941 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Harvard Surgical Unit - newsclippings", 1919 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - "International Organization for Social Welfare", 1946-1952 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - The Junior League Crippled Children's Home, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
  - KEEP (Kiyosato Educations Experiments Project), 1960-1963 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Leprosy, 1965, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Medical Social Service, 1919 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings - Miscellaneous, 1877, 1928, 1941-1961 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous notes - 1947, 1962, 1965, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Notes, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Pamphlets - Buchenwald Camp, Hong Kong, 1944-1946, 1957-1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - "Personal Clippings" of Elizabeth Gardiner, 1947-1948 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - St. Michael's House, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "Seventh International Conference of Social Work," Toronto, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
  - Social Service Study, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - "Survey of the Surgical Discharges", 1913, 1927, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Unitarian Service Committee, 1944-1946 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - UNRRA Mission in Germany: Photographs, 1946-1947 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - UNRRA, 1944-1945 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - UNRRA and other: news clippings, 1944-1946 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Certificates - 1914, 1917, 1927, 1935, 1946, 1950, 1953, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous papers - 1922, 1946, 1953, 1961-1962 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Autographs (notebook), 1918 (Box 12)
  - Printed material
    - Convalescence & Rehabilitation, 1944 (Box 12)
    - Convalescent Care, 1940 (Box 12)
    - Convalescent Care in Great Britain, 1935 (Box 12)
    - The Road to Recovery from Illness, 1945 (Box 12)
- Series III. Photographs and memorabilia
  - Photographs and memorabilia, and postal cards mainly from travel (Box 13)
  - World War I sourvenirs including regiment badges (i.e. RoyalHighlander Black Watch), dog tags, and medals (i.e. Italian Red Cross); currency - foreign and American (1 dated 1750 ); commemorative coins (i.e. Booker T. Washington, 1946 ); tax tokens. Also UNRRA epaulets, insignias and tie. (Box 14)
  - 5 items: diplomas, letters 1908-1909, 1918-1919, 1927 (Mapcase-folder 1)